So running scripts is great.
使用脚本是一种很好的方式
But what if I don't want to have to code an entire script to do some things?
但如果我不想编写一个完整的脚本来做某些事呢？
What if I want to just tinker around with the blockchain?
比如我只是想用区块链做一个测试？
Well, hard hat comes packed with this thing called the console.
Hardhat 有一个自带的功能叫做“控制台”("console")
The console is a JavaScript environment. For us to run JavaScript commands to interact with any blockchain,
控制台是一个 JavaScript 环境，用于运行 JavaScript 命令来和任何区块链进行交互
we can jump to the console by running
我们可以通过以下命令跳转到控制台
yarn, hardhat, console, and then whatever network flag
"yarn hardhat console" 后面可以是任何网络标识
if we want to work on rink B, main net polygon, avalanche, etc.
比如说 Rinkeby, 主网络, polygon, avalanche 等等
That's just network local host.
"-- network localhost"
And now we're dropped into a shell him
现在我们就进入了一个 shell
in the shell, we can do everything that we do in a deploy script.
在这个 shell 里，我们可以做在 deploy 脚本里做的所有事
And we don't even have to run these imports,
我们甚至不需要运行这些导入操作
because everything with hard hat is automatically imported into our console.
因为 Hardhat 里的所有东西都已经在控制台里被自动导入了
So for example, let's say I wanted to get a simple storage contract factory.
举个例子，假设我要获取一个 "SimpleStorage" 的合约工厂
Well, I could run exactly this line here.
那么我可以运行和这一行完全一样的内容
I could say const, simple storage, factory equals await ethers dot get contract factory, have simple storage.
就是 "const SimpleStorageFactory = await ethers.getContractFactory("SimpleStorage")"
And now I can go ahead and even deploy this.
现在，我甚至还要部署它
So I can even just copy this line, paste it.
所以我可以直接复制这一行，粘贴
And if we flip back to our node, we'll see that we just deployed a nother simple storage.
然后回到我们的节点，就可以看到我们刚刚部署了另外一个 "SimpleStorage"
And now we can do things like await simple storage dot retrieve.
现在我还可以做这些事 "await simpleStorage.retrieve"
And I get the return value which is going to be a big number with a value of zero.
并且我得到了一个返回值是 "BigNumber"
I can also make transactions
我还可以发起一次交易
so I can do a weight, simple storage. That store let's do 55
可以这样做 "await simpleStorage.store("55")"
If I hit up twice, I can go back to the simple storage dot retrieve.
如果我按两下上键("↑")，可以回到 "simpleStorage.retrieve"
call that function and I can see my big number has a value of 55. Now,
调用这个函数就可以看到现在是 "BigNumber"
this is a great way to quickly interact with any blockchain that we want.
这是与所有区块链进行快速交互的一种很好的方式
Now you can exit the shell by hitting Ctrl C twice to get out.
现在你可以通过按两次 "Ctrl C" 来退出 shell
Or you can also just you can also Trash Can your terminal if you get confused.
或者你可以直接删除这个终端，如果你觉得麻烦的话
This console works with any network
这个控制台适用于所有网络
we can even do yarn, hard hat console dash dash network hard hat.
我们可以运行 "yarn hardhat console --network hardhat"
And we'll get dropped into a hard hat network.
这样我们就会进入 "Hardhat Network"
Now this is not going to be the same node that's running here,
它与这里的这个节点不是同样的节点
this is going to be one that only runs for the duration of this command.
它只是在这个命令下暂时运行的一个节点
So whenever we cancel this command, this hard hat network gets cancelled.
所以一旦我们退出这个命令，这个 "Hardhat Network" 就会被删除
And close out that too.
再次关闭它
We can also do yarn, hard hat, console, dash dash network Rinkeby Rigby,
我们也可以运行 "yarn hardhat console --network rinkeby"
or polygon or test net or main net or whatever we want.
或者是 polygon, 测试网，主网络或是任何我们想要用的网络
And we can do things like ethers dot provider
我们还可以这样做 "ethers.provider."
that can do things like await ethers dot provider dot get block number,
我们可以运行 "await ethers.provider.getBlockNumber"
see the block number of Rigby.
查看 Rinkeby 的区块编号
We can also deploy contracts, we can update contracts, we can do anything that we want,
我们还可以部署合约，更新合约，以及做任何我们想要做的事情
you can do anything in these consoles,
总之你可以在控制台里做任何事
and they're great ways to quickly test and tinker in interact with contracts.
它是对合约进行快速测试和交互的一种很好的方式